So sometimes I get invited to give weird talks.
أحيانآ أدعى الالقاء محاضرات غريبة الشكل
I got invited to speak to the people
على سبيل المثال لقد تم دعوتي لكي أتحدث الى مجموعة من الناس
who dress up in big stuffed animal costumes
يلبسون أزياء محشوه وكبيرة جدآ على شكل حيوانات
to perform at sporting events.
ليرقصوا في الاحداث الرياضية
Unfortunately I couldn't go.
لللاسف لم أستطع الحضور
But it got me thinking about
ولكن ذلك جعلني أفكر
the fact that these guys, at least most of them,
في حقيقة أن هؤلاء الناس على الاقل معظمهم
know what it is that they do for a living.
يعلمون ماذا يفعلون لكسب عيشهم
What they do is they dress up
أنهم يلبسون
as stuffed animals and entertain people at sporting events.
حيوانات محشية....ويمتعون الناس في الاحداث الرياضية
Shortly after that I got invited
وبعد فتره قصيره من الدعوة السابقة تمت دعوتي
to speak at the convention of the people
للحديث في حشد من الناس
who make balloon animals.
الذين يصنعون بالونات على شكل حيوانات...
And again, I couldn't go. But it's a fascinating group. They make balloon animals.
ومرة أخرى لم استطع ان أذهب.ولكنهم مجموعة رائعة من الناس انهم يصنعون حيوانات من البالونات
There is a big schism between the ones who make
وطبعا هناك فرق بين من يصنع حيوانات
gospel animals and porn animals, but --
محترمة وحيوانات خليعة
(Laughter)
:)
they do a lot of really cool stuff with balloons.
ولكنهم حقا يصنعون أشكال ممتازه بالبالونات
Sometimes they get in trouble, but not often.
ولكنهم أحيانا يقعون في المشاكل ولكن ليس دائمًا
And the other thing about these guys
وهناك شي أخر اريد أن أنوه عنه عن هؤلاء الناس
is, they also know what they do for a living.
أنهم ايضآ يعلمون ماذا يفعلون
They make balloon animals.
أنه يصنعون حيوانات من البالونات
But what do we do for a living?
ماذا عنا نحن ماذا نفل لكسب لقمة عيشنا
What exactly to the people watching this do every day?
بالتحديد الناس الذين يشاهدونا ماذا تفعلون كل يوم
And I want to argue that what we do
وأنا اريد أن اجادلكم بأننا
is we try to change everything.
نحاول أن نغير كل شي
That we try to find a piece of the status quo --
و في بعض الاحيان نحاول ان نستغل الوضع الراهن
something that bothers us, something that needs to be improved,
لتغير أشياء تزعجنا او اشياء نريد ان نطورها
something that is itching to be changed -- and we change it.
وفي أحيان كثيره تصيبنا هذه الاشياء التي نريد ان نغيرها بحكة شدية فنغيرها
We try to make big, permanent, important change.
ونحاول ايضا ان نصنع تغيرات مهمة وكبيرة ودائمة
But we don't think about it that way.
ولكننا لا نفكر بها بهذه الطريقة
And we haven't spent a lot of time talking about
و ايضا لا نمضي وقت كافي للتفكير بها
what that process is like.
وكيفية نشات هذه العملية
And I've been studying it for a couple years.
وانني ادرس هذه العملية لبضع سنوات الان
And I want to share a couple stories with you today.
واريد أن أشارككم اليوم ببعض القصص
First, about a guy named Nathan Winograd.
أول قصة عن شخص يدعى نيثن وين جراد
Nathan was the number two person at the San Francisco SPCA.
نيثن كان الرجل الثاني في سان فرانسيسكو SPCA
And what you may not know about the history of the SPCA
والذي لا تعرفونه عن تاريخ SPCA
is, it was founded to kill dogs and cats.
أنها أنشأت لقتل الكلاب والقطط
Cities gave them a charter
لقد تعاقدت معهم المدن
to get rid of the stray animals on the street and destroy them.
للتخلص من الحيوانات الضالة في الشوارع وقتلها
In a typical year four million dogs and cats were killed,
في حوالي السنة تم قتل أربعة ملايين كلب وقطة
most of them within 24 hours of being scooped off of the street.
معظمهم تم حصدهم من الشوارع في 24 ساعة
Nathan and his boss saw this,
وشهد ذالك نيثن رئيسه في العمل
and they could not tolerate it.
ولم يستطيعوا التسامح في ذلك
So they set out to make San Francisco
لذلك عزموا على جعل سان فرانسيسكو
a no-kill city:
مدينة بدون قتل
create an entire city
و إنشاء مدينة بأكملها
where every dog and cat,
حيث كل كلب او قط
unless it was ill or dangerous,
إلا إذا كان مريضا أو خطرة
would be adopted, not killed.
أن يتم تبنيه وليس قتله
And everyone said it was impossible.
وقال الجميع أنها مهمة مستحيلة
Nathan and his boss went to the city council to get a change in the ordinance.
نيثن ورئيسه ذهبوا الي مجلس المدينة لتغير القرار الرسمي
And people from SPCAs and humane shelters around the country
والناس من SPCAs و حتى الملاجئ الإنسانية حول البلاد
flew to San Francisco
تدفقوا لـــ سان فرانسيسكو
to testify against them --
ليشهدوا ضضهم
to say it would hurt the movement and it was inhumane.
ويقولوا أن ذلك سيضر الحركة وان ذلك لا أخلاقي
They persisted. And Nathan went directly to the community.
وظلت الحملة مستمرة.فتوجه نيثن مباشرة الى المجتمع
He connected with people who cared about this:
وتواصل مع الناس الذين يهمهم هذا الامر
nonprofessionals, people with passion.
أناس عاديين ولكنهم متعاطفون مع الفكرة
And within just a couple years,
وخلال سنوات معدودة
San Francisco became the first no-kill city,
أصبحت سان فرانسيسكو أول مدينة بدون قتل
running no deficit, completely supported by the community.
بدون أي مضار تذكر ومدعمة بشكل كامل من قبل المواطننين
Nathan left and went to Tompkins County, New York --
وغادر نيثن الى تبكن كونتي نيورك
a place as different from San Francisco
مكان مختلف تماما عن سان فراسيسكو
as you can be and still be in the United States. And he did it again.
قدر المستطاع ولكن ضمن الولايات المتحدة وقد فعلها مرة أخرى
He went from being a glorified dogcatcher
لقد تحول من صائد للكلاب
to completely transforming the community.
الى رجل مؤثر في المجتمع
And then he went to North Carolina and did it again.
وبعد ذلك ذهب الى نورث كالورينا وفعلها مرة أخرى
And he went to Reno and he did it again.
والى رينو وفعلها مرة اخرى
And when I think about what Nathan did,
وعندما أفكر فيما فعل نيثن
and when I think about what people here do, I think about ideas.
مقارنة بما يفعله الناس هنا .... أنها مسالة أفكار
And I think about the idea that
وعندما افكر في هذه اﻻفكار
creating an idea, spreading an idea
من صناعة الفكرة الى نشرها
has a lot behind it.
هناك الكثير ورائها
I don't know if you've ever been to a Jewish wedding,
ﻻ اعلم أذا كنتم حضرتم زفاف على الطريقة اليهودية
but what they do is, they take a light bulb
انهم ياخذون مصباح كهربائي
and they smash it.
ويحطموه
Now there is a bunch of reasons for that, and stories about it.
وهناك أسباب عديدة لذلك وقصص كثيرة حول هذا التقليد
But one reason is because it indicates a change,
أحد هذه اﻻسباب أنه يشير الى التغير
from before to after.
ما قبل الزواج وبعده
It is a moment in time.
في لحظة من الزمن
And I want to argue that we are living through
واريد ان اجادلكم .... نحن نعيش خلال
and are right at the key moment
فترة زمنية
of a change in the way ideas are created
تغير فيها طريقة صنع اﻻفكار
and spread and implemented.
وطريقة نشرها وتطبيقها
We started with the factory idea:
أذا بدانا بفكرة جوهرية
that you could change the whole world if you had an efficient factory
يمكننا ان نغير العالم بهذه الفكرة الجوهرية
that could churn out change.
ونحدث تغيرا عنيفا وقويا
We then went to the TV idea,
عندما ذهبنا الى التلفاز
that said if you had a big enough mouthpiece,
كان هناك مقولة مشهورة تقول أذا كان عندك حضور كبير
if you could get on TV enough times, if you could buy enough ads, you could win.
ووقت كافي على التلفاز لبيع أعلاناتك سوف تربح بالتاكيد
And now we're in this new model of leadership,
ونحن الان عند مفهوم جديد الزعامة
where the way we make change
بالزعامة يمكننا ان نغير
is not by using money
ليس بالنفوذ المالي
or power to lever a system,
أو بالقوة لتغير اي نظام
but by leading.
ولكن بالزعامة
So let me tell you about the three cycles. The first one is the factory cycle.
دعني أسرد لكم عن الدوائر الثلاثة الاولى وهي دائرة التصنيع
Henry Ford comes up with a really cool idea.
وقد جاء هنري فور بفكره جيده
It enables him to hire men
تجعله يوظف أناس
who used to get paid 50 cents a day
كانوا ياخذون 50 سنتا في اليوم
and pay them five dollars a day.
ويدفع لهم خمسة دولارات في اليوم
Because he's got an efficient enough factory.
الانه كان عنده مصانع كثيرة
Well with that sort of advantage
وبهذه الميزة التي عنده
you can churn out a lot of cars.
كان يمكنه ان ينتج الكثير من السيارات
You can make a lot of change. You can get roads built.
ويمكنك ان تفعل الكثير من التغيرات كبناء طرق
You can change the fabric of an entire country.
ويمكنك بهذه الطريقه ان تغير نسيج المجتمع لبلد بالكامل
That the essence of what you're doing is you need
وجوهر هذه الفكرة أن كل ما تريده هو
ever-cheaper labor,
عمالة رخيصة
and ever-faster machines.
وماكينات سريعة
And the problem we've run into is, we're running out of both.
والمشكلة الان اننا قد نقذ منا الاثنين
Ever-cheaper labor and ever-faster machines.
العمالة الرخيصة والماكينات السريعة
(Laughter)
:)
So we shift gears for a minute,
ساخرج عن الموضوع لدقيقة
and say, "I know: television;
أنا أعرف التلفاز
advertising. Push push.
أعلانات... ـدتفق...تدفق
Take a good idea and push it on the world.
خذ فكرة جيدة وادفعها للعالم
I have a better mousetrap.
أنا لدي مصيدة فئران افضل
And if I can just get enough money to tell enough people, I'll sell enough."
سابيع أفضل أذا كان لدي المال الكافي الاخبر عدد أكثر من الناس
And you can build an entire industry on that.
ويمكنك ان تبني صناعة كاملة على هذه الفكرة
If necessary you can put babies in your ads.
وإذا كان ضروريا يمكنك ان تضع الاطفال في أعلاناتك
If necessary you can use babies to sell other stuff.
وإذا كان ضروريا يمكنك أن تستخدم الاطفال لتبيع اشياء أخرى
And if babies don't work, you can use doctors.
وإذا لم تنفع طريقة الاطفال يمكنك أن تستخدم الاطباء
But be careful.
ولكن كن حذرآ
Because you don't want to get an unfortunate juxtaposition,
لأنك لا تريد أن تحصل على مجاورة مؤسفة
where you're talking about one thing instead of the other.
وانت تتكلم عن شي وتجد شي عكسي له مجاور له
(Laughter)
:)
This model requires you to act like the king,
وهذ النموذج يتطلب منك التصرف مثل الملك
like the person in the front of the room
كاشخص أمام غرفعه
throwing things to the peons in the back.
يلقي بأشياء الاشخاص الذين خلفه
That you are in charge, and you're going to tell people
أنت المسؤل وانك ستقول للناس
what to do next.
ماذا ستفعلون بعد ذلك
The quick little diagram of it is, you're up here,
ويوضح هذا الرسم البياني ذلك
and you are pushing it out to the world.
أنك تدفع الفكرة او المنتج الى العالم
This method -- mass marketing --
هذه هي طريقة التسويق الجماهيري
requires average ideas,
تتطلب أفكار متوسطة
because you're going to the masses,
الانك سوف تقوم بنشرها على نطاق واسع
and plenty of ads.
واعلانات بكميات هائلة
What we've done as spammers
لقد فعلنا كما يفعل ناشرو البريد المزعج الاسبامرز
is tried to hypnotize everyone
يحاولون أن ينومونا مغناطيسيا
into buying our idea,
لشراء فكرتهم
hypnotize everyone into donating to our cause,
نومهم جميعا لتصل الى غايتك
hypnotize everyone into voting for our candidate.
نومهم جميعا ليصوتوا لك
And, unfortunately, it doesn't work so well anymore either.
والمشكلة ان هذه الفكرة أيضا لاتعمل جيدا الان
(Laughter)
:)
But there is good news around the corner -- really good news.
ولكن هناك اخبار جيدة في الافق... حقا جيدة
I call it the idea of tribes.
أنا أسميها طريقة القبائل
What tribes are, is a very simple concept
ماهي طريقة القبائل أنه مبداء بسيط
that goes back 50,000 years.
أنه يرجع الي 50 الف سنه
It's about leading and connecting people and ideas.
توصيل الناس والافكر ببعضهم البعض عن طريق قيادتم
And it's something that people have wanted forever.
وهذا شي أحتاجه الناس من قديم الازل
Lots of people are used to having a spiritual tribe, or a church tribe,
كثير من الناس شكلوا قبائل روحية او قبائل دينية
having a work tribe,
عندنا قبائل مكونه من عمال
having a community tribe.
عندنا قبائل اجتماعية
But now, thanks to the internet, thanks to the explosion of mass media,
ولكن الان الفضل يعود الانترنت وانفجار وسائل الإعلام الجماهيرية
thanks to a lot of other things
والشكر الاشياء كثيرة أخرى
that are bubbling through our society around the world,
لقد تفشت في المجتمعات حول العالم
tribes are everywhere.
القبائل في كل مكان
The Internet was supposed to homogenize everyone by connecting us all.
كانت وظيفةالانترنت هي جعل الناس متجانسون بوصلهم ببعضهم البعض
Instead what it's allowed is silos of interest.
ولكن الانترنت على العكس شكل علاقة من المصالح المشتركة
So you've got the red-hat ladies over here.
لديك مجموعة من السيدات اصحاب القبعات الحمراء هنا
You've got the red-hat triathletes over there.
ولديك مجموعة أخرى من الرياضيين أصحاب الأطقم الحمراء هناك
You've got the organized armies over here.
ولديك مجموعة من الجنود المنظمين كذلك
You've got the disorganized rebels over here.
ولدينا ايضا مجموعة غير منظمة من المتمردين
You've got people in white hats making food.
لديك مجموعة من الناس أصحاب القبعات البيضاء يعدون الطعام
And people in white hats sailing boats.
ومجموعة اخرى من أصحاب القبعات البيضاء يبحرون بالمراكب الشراعية
The point is that you can find Ukrainian folk dancers
المقصود هو أنه يمكنك أن تجد مجموعة من الراقصين الاوكارنيين
and connect with them,
وتتواصل معهم
because you want to be connected.
لانك ببساطه تحب ذلك
That people on the fringes
وبالاضافة الى ذلك
can find each other, connect and go somewhere.
ويمكنهم العثور على بعضهم البعض والاتصال والذهاب الى اي مكان
Every town that has a volunteer fire department
أي مدينة لديها أطفائيون متطوعون
understands this way of thinking.
يفهمون تلك الطريقة من التفكير
(Laughter)
:)
Now it turns out
الآن اتضح
this is a legitimate non-photoshopped photo.
ذلك حقيقي وليست صورة مصطنعة
People I know who are firemen told me that this is not uncommon.
الناس الذين اعرفهم من رجال الاطفاء أخبروني أن ذلك غير استثنائي
And that what firemen do to train sometimes
وان هذا مايفعله الاطفائيون للتدريب في بعض الاحيان
is they take a house that is going to be torn down,
ياخذون بيت سيتم هدمه
and they burn it down instead, and practice putting it out.
ويحرقونه بدلا من هدمه ويتدربون عليه
But they always stop and take a picture.
ولاكنهم لاينسون ابدا ان ياخذوا صورة
(Laughter)
:)
You know the pirate tribe is a fascinating one.
أتعلمون قبائل القراصنة مذهلون
They've got their own flag. They've got the eye patches.
لديهم علمهم الخاص وعصابة العين
You can tell when you're running into someone in a tribe.
يمكنك أن تقول اذا ذهبت الى أحد هذه الجماعات
And it turns out that it's tribes --
يمكنك القول بأ ن القبائل
not money, not factories --
ليس المال أو المصانع
that can change our world, that can change politics,
سيغيرو العالم
that can align large numbers of people.
الانها تستطيع أن تنظم مجموعة كبيرة من الناس
Not because you force them to do something against their will,
ليس الانك تجبرهم ان يفعلو شي خارج عن ارادتهم
but because they wanted to connect.
ولكن اﻻنهم يريدون ذلك
That what we do for a living now,
ذلك ما نفعله الان لكسب لقمة العيش
all of us, I think,
جميعنا على ما اعتقد
is find something worth changing,
أذا وجدنا شي جدير بالتغير
and then assemble tribes that assemble tribes
أحشد قبيلتك والتي بدورها ستحشد قبائل اخرى
that spread the idea and spread the idea.
وذلك سينشر الفكرة
And it becomes something far bigger than ourselves,
وتصبح شى اكبر منا
it becomes a movement.
تصبح حركة او صحوة
So when Al Gore set out
عندما اراد ال جور
to change the world again,
ان يغير العالم من جديد
he didn't do it by himself.
لم يفعلها بنفسه
And he didn't do it by buying a lot of ads.
ولم يفعلها بشراء الكثير من اﻻعلانات
He did it by creating a movement.
لقد فعلها بتشكيل حركة
Thousands of people around the country
بواسطة اﻻف من الناس حول الوطن
who could give his presentation for him,
من الذي قدمه للناس
because he can't be in 100 or 200 or 500 cities in each night.
اﻻنه ﻻيستطيع ان يكون في 100 او 200 او 500 مدينة في ليلة واحدة
You don't need everyone.
انك ﻻ تحتاج الجميع
What Kevin Kelley has taught us is you just need,
وقد علمنا كافين كيلي انك فقط تحتاج
I don't know, a thousand true fans --
ﻻ اعلم 1000 مشجع للفكرة بصدق
a thousand people who care enough
الف شخص مهتمين بحق
that they will get you the next round
سيربحون الجولة القادمة
and the next round and the next round.
والتي تليها
And that means that the idea you create, the product you create,
وهذا يعني الفكرة التي صنعتها هي المنتج
the movement you create isn't for everyone,
الحركة التي صنعتها ليست للجميع
it's not a mass thing. That's not what this is about.
انه ليس تسويقا جماهيري
What it's about instead
ولكنه
is finding the true believers.
ولكنه البحث عن مخلصين حقيقين
It's easy to look at what I've said so far,
من السهل النظر فيما ذكرته حتى اﻻن
and say, "Wait a minute, I don't have what it takes to be that kind of leader."
والقول ولكني لست لدي مهارات القيادة
So here are two leaders. They don't have a lot in common.
هناك نوعيني من القادة ليس لديهم قواسم مشتركة كثيرة
They're about the same age. But that's about it.
المشترك بيهما انهما في نفس العمر
What they did, though, is each in their own way,
ولكن لكل منهم له طريقته الخاصة
created a different way
وصنعوا طريقة مختلفة
of navigating your way through technology.
للتبحر في التكنلوجيا
So some people will go out and get people to be on one team.
وهناك اناس سيخرجون ويحضرون أناس الى الفريق
And some people will get people to be on the other team.
وأناس أخرين سيحضرون أناس ليكونوا في الفريق الاخر
It also informs the decisions you make
وذلك سيعزز القرار الذي ستاخذه
when you make products or services.
عندما تصنع منتج اوخدمة
You know, this is one of my favorite devices.
هل تعلمون هذا واحد من الاجهزة المفضلة لدى
But what a shame that it's not organized
ولكن يالا العار انه غير منظم
to help authors create movements.
ليساعد المؤلفون ليصنعوا حركة
What would happen if, when you're using your Kindle,
ماذا سيحدث عندما تستخدم جهاز كنديل (جهاز لقرائة الكتب من أمزون)
you could see the comments and quotes and notes
يمكنك أن ترى التعليقات والاقتباسات والملاحضات
from all the other people reading the same book as you in that moment.
من جميع الناس الذين يقراؤن نفس الكتاب في نفس اللحظة
Or from your book group. Or from your friends, or from the circle you want.
او من مجموعة مهتمه بالكتب او من اصدقائك او من اي دائرة تريدها
What would happen if authors, or people with ideas
ماذا سيحدث أذا استطاع الناس اوالمؤلفون او ناس ذو افكار
could use version two, which comes out on Monday,
أستخدام الاصدارة الثانية والتي ستظهر يوم الاثنين
and use it to organize people
واستخدموها لتنظيم الناس
who want to talk about something.
لمن يريد ان يتكلم عن اي شي
Now there is a million things I could share with you about the mechanics here.
هناك الملاين من الاشياء التي يمكن ان اشارككم بها عن المحرك لهذه الاشياء.
But let me just try a couple.
ولكن دعوني اجرب اخبركم بالقليل منها
The Beatles did not invent teenagers.
فريق البيتلز لم يخترعوا المراهقون
They merely decided to lead them.
انهم فقط قرروا ان يقودوهم
That most movements, most leadership that we're doing
هكذا تفعل معظم الحركات ومعظم الزعامات
is about finding a group that's disconnected
هي عبارة عن البحث عن مجموعة من الناس غير مترابطين
but already has a yearning --
ولكن لديهم لهفة
not persuading people to want something
أنه ليس اقناع الناس بامتلاك شي
they don't have yet.
لايملكونه حتى الان
When Diane Hatz worked on "The Meatrix,"
عندما عملت داني هيز في متاريكس
her video that spread all across the internet
أنتشر الفديو في ارجاء الانترنت
about the way farm animals are treated,
وكان حول كيف تعامل حيونات المزارع
she didn't invent the idea of being a vegan.
أنا لم تخترع فكرة كن نباتيا
She didn't invent the idea of caring about this issue.
وانها ايضا لم تخترع الاهتمام بهذه المشكلة
But she helped organize people,
ولكنها ساعدة في تنظيم الناس
and helped turn it into a movement.
وساعدتهم لتصبح حركة
Hugo Chavez did not invent the disaffected
هيجو شافيز لم يخترع الساخطون
middle and lower class of Venezuela. He merely led them.
ولكنه بالكاد قاد الطبقة الوسطى والمعدمون في فنزولا
Bob Marley did not invent Rastafarians.
بوب مارلي لم يخترع الرستافارس (Rastafarians.)
He just stepped up and said, "Follow me."
ولكنه وقف وقال اتبعوني
Derek Sivers invented CD Baby,
ديرك سيفيرز اخترع CD Baby
which allowed independent musicians
والذي يسمح للموسيقين المستقلين
to have a place to sell their music without selling out to the man --
ببيع موسيقاهم من غير ان بيعهم لهم
to have place to take the mission
ولكنه صنع مكان يمكنهم ان ينطلقوا منه
they already wanted to go to, and connect with each other.
انهم ارادو ذلك وتواصلوا مع بعضهم البعض
What all these people have in common is that they are heretics.
ما المشترك بين كل هؤلاء الناس انهم مهرتقون
That heretics look at the status quo and say,
ينظر المهرتقون للوضع الراهن ويقولون
"This will not stand. I can't abide this status quo.
لن أقف مكتوف الايدي لن امتثل للوضع الراهن
I am willing to stand up and be counted and move things forward.
وأنا على استعداد للوقوف والتصدي والمضي قدما
I see what the status quo is; I don't like it."
أنا أرى ما هو الوضع الراهن. أنا لا أحبه .
That instead of looking at all the little rules
بدلا من أن يحقق في جميع القواعد قليلا
and following each one of them,
ويتبع كل واحدة منها
that instead of being what I call a sheepwalker --
وهذا ما اسميه راعي الغنم
somebody who's half asleep,
شخص نصف نائم
following instructions,
يتبع التعليمات
keeping their head down, fitting in --
خافضين رؤسهم محاولين التأقلم
every once in a while someone stands up and says, "Not me."
وبين الفينة والاخرى شخص ما يقف ويقول لست أنا
Someone stands up and says, "This one is important.
شخص ما يقف ويقول هذا في غاية الاهمية
We need to organize around it."
نحن بحاجة إلى تنظيم حول هذه الفكرة
And not everyone will. But you don't need everyone.
ولكن لن يفعل الجميع وانت لا تحتاج الى الجميع
You just need a few people --
انك في حاجة الى عدد قليل من الناس
(Laughter) --
:)
who will look at the rules,
من الذي سينظر في القواعد والقوانين
realize they make no sense,
ويكتشف ان لا معنى لها
and realize how much they want to be connected.
ويدرك اننا نريد ان نتواصل
So Tony Hsieh does not run a shoe store.
لذلك توني شيا لا يدير محل احذية الان
Zappos isn't a shoe store.
متجر الاحذية Zappos
Zappos is the one, the only,
Zappos أنه الوحيد
the best-there-ever-was
أفضل من أي وقت مضى
place for people who are into shoes to find each other,
انه مكان لصانعي الاحذيةالايجاد بعضهم البعض
to talk about their passion,
للتكلم عن شغفهم
to connect with people who care more
والتواصل مع أناس مهتمين اكثر
about customer service than making a nickel tomorrow.
يتكلمون حول خدمة العملاء وليس كيف سنجمع المال غذا
It can be something as prosaic as shoes,
يمكن ان يكون شي غير ممتع كلاحذية
and something as complicated as overthrowing a government.
أو موضوع معقد كاطاحة الحكومة
It's exactly the same behavior though.
ولكنه نفس المنهج
What it requires, as Geraldine Carter has discovered,
كل ما هو مطلوب كما اكتشف جلديني كارتير
is to be able to say, "I can't do this by myself.
أنا لا أستطيع ان افعل ذلك وحدي
But if I can get other people to join my Climb and Ride,
ولكن أذا كنت أستطيع أن أجعل اناس اخرين ينضمون الي ويتسلقون ويركبوا معي
then together we can get something that we all want.
عندها سنحصل جميعا على ما نريد
We're just waiting for someone to lead us."
نحن فقط ننتظر من يقودنا
Michelle Kaufman has pioneered
مشيل كوفمان الرائدة
new ways of thinking about environmental architecture.
في الطريقة الجديدة العمارة البيئية
She doesn't do it by quietly building one house at a time.
أنها لم تفعلها ببساطة عن طريق بناء منزل واحد في كل مرة
She does it by telling a story
لقد فعلتها بسرد قصة
to people who want to hear it.
الاشخان يريدون ان يستمعوا لها
By connecting a tribe of people
والتواصل مع قبيلة من الناس
who are desperate to be connected to each other.
ومتشوقون الاتصال ببعضهم البعض
By leading a movement and
وقيادة الحركة
making change.
واحداث تغير
And around and around and around it goes.
ومن حولها تدور الاحداث مرار وتكرار
So three questions I'd offer you.
اريد ان اعرض عليكم ثلاثة اسئلة
The first one is, who exactly
الاول من بالضبط
are you upsetting?
أنت تزعج ؟
Because if you're not upsetting anyone, you're not changing the status quo.
لانه اذا كنت لا تزعج احدا انت لا تغير في الوضع الراهن
The second question is, who are you connecting?
السؤال الثاني مع من تتواصل؟
Because for a lot of people, that's what they're in it for:
لانه بالنسبة للكثير من الناس هذا مايريدونه
the connections that are being made, one to the other.
الاتصال ببعضهم البعض
And the third one is, who are you leading?
والثالث هو من تقود ؟
Because focusing on that part of it --
لانه يجب التركيز على هذا الجانب
not the mechanics of what you're building,
وليس الماكينات التي تبني ما تصنع
but the who, and the leading part -- is where change comes.
ولكن في سؤال من تقود هنا ياتي التغير
So Blake, at Tom's Shoes, had a very simple idea.
بليك في توم الاحذية كان عنده فكرة بسيطة
"What would happen if every time someone bought a pair of these shoes
ماذا سيحدث عندما يشتري أحد زوج من هذه الاحذية
I gave exactly the same pair to someone
أعطى نفس زوج تماما لشخص أخر
who doesn't even own a pair of shoes?"
والذي لا يملك أصلا زوج من الاحذية ؟
This is not the story of how you get shelf space at Neiman Marcus.
أنا ليست قصة كيف اجد لي رف في محلات Neiman Marcus
It's a story of a product that tells a story.
انها قصة منتج يخبر قصة
And as you walk around with this remarkable pair of shoes
وعندما تمشي بزوج الاحذية الافت للنظر
and someone says, "What are those?"
ويقول لك احدهم ماهذا؟
You get to tell the story on Blake's behalf,
ستخبرهم بقصة عن بليك
on behalf of the people who got the shoes.
وقصة الناس اذين أبتاعوا الحذاء
And suddenly it's not one pair of shoes or 100 pairs of shoes.
وفجأة انه ليس زوج من الاحذية او 100زوج
It's tens of thousands of pairs of shoes.
بل عشرات الآلاف من الازواج من الاحذية
My friend Red Maxwell has spent the last 10 years
صديقي ريد ماكسويل قضى عشر سنوات من حياته
fighting against juvenile diabetes.
يحارب ضدد مرض السكري
Not fighting the organization that's fighting it -- fighting with them, leading them,
لا يحارب المؤسسة التي تحارب المرض ولكنه يحارب معهم ويقوضهم
connecting them, challenging the status quo
يجعلهم يتواصلون متحدي الوضع الراهن
because it's important to him.
لانه شي مهم بالنسبة له
And the people he surrounds himself with need the connection.
والناس الذين احاط نفسه بهم يريدون ذلك التواصل
They need the leadership. It makes a difference.
انهم يريدون قياته لهم ليحدثوا الغير
You don't need permission from people to lead them.
أنت لاتريد اذن من الناس لتقودهم
But in case you do, here it is:
ولكن في حالة انك منتظر الاذن
they're waiting, we're waiting
أنهم ينتظرون وينتظرون
for you to show us where to go next.
لتوضح لنا أي نذهب بعد ذلك.
So here is what leaders have in common. The first thing is, they challenge
هذا ما يشترك فيه القادة الامر الاول انهم يتحدون
the status quo.
الوضع الراهن
They challenge what's currently there.
انه يتحدون ما هو اصلا موجود
The second thing is, they build a culture.
ثانيا انهم يبنون ثقافة
A secret language, a seven-second handshake,
لغة سرية كمصافحة سريعة لمدة سبع ثوان
a way of knowing that you're in or out.
طريقة لمعرفة معنا ام لا
They have curiosity. Curiosity about people in the tribe,
لديهم اهتمام وفضول بالاشخاص في قبيلتهم
curiosity about outsiders. They're asking questions.
لديهم فضول واهتمام بغرباء عنهم باشخاص لديهم أسئلة
They connect people to one another.
ويربطون الناس بعضهم بعضا
Do you know what people want more than anything?
هل تعلم ماذا يريد الناس أكثر من اي شي
They want to be missed.
يريد احد ان يفتقدهم
They want to be missed the day they don't show up.
في اليوم الذي لا يظهرون اويذهبوا فيه
They want to be missed when they're gone.
يريد احد ان يفتقدهم في اليوم الذي يرحلون فيه عن العالم
And tribe leaders can do that.
و زعماء القبيلة يستطيعون فعل ذلك
It's fascinating, because all tribe leaders have charisma,
رائع الان كل القادة لهم الكاريزما (جاذبية)
but you don't need charisma to become a leader.
ولكنكا لاتريد كاريزما لتصبع قائد
Being a leader gives you charisma.
ولكن القيادة تعطيك الكاريزما
If you look and study the leaders who have succeeded,
اذا نظرت ودرست القادة الناجحون
that's where charisma comes from -- from the leading.
ستجد ان الكريزما جائت من قيادتهم للناس
Finally, they commit.
اخيرا انهم يلتزمون
They commit to the cause. They commit to the tribe.
يلتزمون للسبب يلتزمون لقبيلتهم
They commit to the people who are there.
يلتزمون للناس الذين يقودوهم
So I'd like you to do something for me.
ولذلك اريدكم ان تفعلوا شي لي
And I hope you'll think about it before you reject it out-of-hand.
واتمنى عليك التفكير في الامر قبل ورفضه قبل خروج الامرعن نطاق السيطرة.
What I want you to do, it only takes 24 hours,
ما اريده منك سياخد منك فقط 24 ساعة
is: create a movement.
هو خلق حركة
Something that matters. Start. Do it. We need it.
شيء ما يهم ....أبدء....أفعلها...نحن نحتاجها
Thank you very much. I appreciate it.
شكرا جزيلا.....أقدر لكم ذلك
(Applause)
تصفيق